Ruth S. Peale Papers
Ruth S. Peale Papers
1950-1965
Peale, Ruth Stafford, 1906-2008.
23.0 linear ft. (ca.)
Papers of the American businesswoman, writer, editor, speaker and church leader; wife of clergyman Norman Vincent Peale. Collection contains correspondence, organizational records, business and financial records, and manuscripts pertaining to the National Council of Churches, the Foundation for Christian Living, the Reformed Church in America, and other organizations. Correspondents of note include Smiley Blanton, Billy Graham, Leonard LeSourd, and Norman Vincent Peale.
149463
Biographical History
Ruth Stafford Peale (1906-2008) was an American businesswoman, writer, editor, speaker and church leader. She was the wife of clergyman Norman Vincent Peale, and co-founder of Guideposts magazine and the Peale Center.
Born Ruth Stafford in Fonds, Iowa on September 10, 1906, she graduated from Syracuse University in 1928 and taught mathematics at Central High School. She married Norman Vincent Peale on June 20, 1930 and shortly began acting as his business manager and representing the family in committee work. She has been an active leader in denominational and interdenominational activities, including serving as vice president of the National Council of Churches and of the Board of Domestic Missions of the Reformed Church in America, as chairman of religion for the New York State Federation of Women's Clubs, as vice chairman o f the Broadcasting and Film Commission of the National Council of Churches, and chairman of the American Mothers Committee. She also appeared with her husband on the television program, "What's Your Trouble?"
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Ruth S. Peale Papers are divided into two series: National Council of Churches, and General File.
National Council of Churches contains correspondence, organizational records, committee reports and published material dealing with-the various activities of the National Council of Churches, for which Mrs. Peale served as vice president. Included in this file is material on such activities as. the Broadcasting and Film Commission, General Board, Finance Committee and the United Church Women.
General files contains correspondence, sermons and articles, financial reports, as well as some organizational records for both the Foundation for Christian Living and The Reformed Church in America. Among the manuscripts are articles by Mrs. Peale entitled "When My Husband Nearly Left The Church" and "Brides To Be." The correspondence contains family letters, business correspondence and social correspondence, including letters to and from Lowell Thomas, Jr., Billy Graham, Dr. Smiley Blanton, Dr. Peale and Leonard Le Sourd.
Arrangement of the Collection
National Council of Churches material is arranged alphabetically by major departments and their subdivisions, with separate files for the following years: 1950-1953, 1954-1957, 1958-1960, and 1061-1965.
General files are arranged alphabetically by subject in two groups, 1954-1961 and 1957-1959.
Related Material
See also the
Norman Vincent Peale Papers
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Church and clergy; Popular culture; Religion and philosophy; Blanton, Smiley, 1882-1966.; Graham, Billy, 1918-; LeSourd, Leonard E.; Peale, Norman Vincent, 1898-1993.; Peale, Ruth Stafford, 1906-2008.; Thomas, Lowell, 1892-1981.; Foundation for Christian Living.; National Council of the Churches of Christ in the United States of America.; Reformed Church in America.; Spouses of clergy.; Businesswomen.; Women in church work.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Written permission of George Hart required to view materials in this collection.
Inventory
- National Council of Churches
  - Analysis of memberships for major units, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Board of Managers, Department of Public Relations Committee on Study and Adjustment (Box 1)
  - General Assembly Minutes (Box 1)
  - General Board (Box 1)
  - General Board, Rules of Procedure (Box 1)
  - General
    - Special Committee on Policy and Strategy (Box 2)
    - Subcommittee on Public Relations (Box 2)
  - Broadcasting and Film Commission
    - Administrative Committee (Box 2)
    - Board of Managers (Box 2)
    - Executive Committee (Box 2)
    - Finance (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Protestant (Box 2)
  - Migrant (Box 2)
  - Migrant appeals (Box 2)
  - Migrants, speaking material (Box 3)
  - United Church Women
    - Administrative Policy (Box 3)
    - Assembly (Box 3)
    - Board of Managers (Box 3)
    - Executive (Box 3)
    - Finance (Box 3)
    - National Laywomen's and Men's Committee (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - 1954-1957
    - Reformed Church in America (Box 3)
    - N.C.C. General, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - N.C.C. General, Board of Domestic Missions, 1955 (Box 3)
    - Business and Finance
      - General, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Executive Committee (Box 4)
      - Executive Committee (Box 5)
    - Chicago Office (Box 5)
    - Committee to restudy committed fund (Box 5)
    - General Assembly, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - General Board (Box 5)
    - General Budget Committee (Box 5)
    - General Budget Committee (Box 6)
    - General Personnel Committee, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - General Policy and Strategy Committee (Box 6)
    - General Policy and Strategy Committee (Box 7)
    - General National Lay Committee (Box 7)
    - General Subcommittee on Publication Operations (Box 7)
    - Washington Memos (Box 8)
    - Broadcasting and Film Commission
      - General, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Board of Managers, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Broadcast Training Committee (Box 8)
      - Committee on Research (Box 8)
      - Executive Committee, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Film Committee (Box 9)
      - Finance Committee, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Joint Commission (Box 9)
      - Radio Committee (Box 9)
      - Special Committee of Ten (Box 9)
      - Television Committee (Box 9)
    - Division of Home Missions
      - General, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Assembly (Box 9)
      - Administrative Committee (Box 9)
      - Executive Board (Box 9)
      - Executive Board (Box 10)
      - Committee on Migrant Work
        - General (Box 10)
        - Subcommittee on Finance, 2 folders (Box 10)
        - Special Events, 2 folders (Box 10)
      - Finance (Box 10)
      - General Board (Box 10)
    - Interchurch Center
      - General (Box 11)
      - Board of Trustees (Box 11)
      - Building Committee, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Executive Committee of Building Committee (Box 11)
      - Fund Raising Committee (Box 11)
    - United Church Women
      - General (Box 11)
      - Board of Managers (Box 11)
      - Executive Committee (Box 12)
      - Fellowship Fund (Box 12)
      - Finance Committee (Box 12)
      - Joint Committee, 2 folders (Box 12)
      - Personnel Committee (Box 12)
      - Retirement Plan Committee (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous
      - "Let There be Light", 2 folders (Box 12)
      - Little Josephine, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - 1958-1960
    - General Business and Finance (Box 13)
    - General Board, 5 folders (Box 13)
    - General Board (Box 14)
    - General Policy and Strategy Committee (Box 14)
    - General Study and Adjustment Committee (Box 14)
    - General Subcommittee on Public Relations (Box 14)
    - General Subcommittee on Publications Operations (Box 14)
    - Broadcasting and Film Commission
      - General (Box 14)
      - Board of Managers (Box 14)
      - Executive Committee (Box 14)
      - Finance Committee (Box 15)
    - Division of Home Missions
      - Administrative Committee (Box 15)
    - Interchurch Center
      - [General], 2 folders (Box 15)
      - Board of Trustees (Box 16)
      - Building Committee (Box 16)
      - Chapel Committee (Box 16)
      - Executive Committee (Box 16)
      - Finance (Box 16)
      - General Business and Finance Committee (Box 16)
      - Operating Committee (Box 16)
    - United Church Women
      - General (Box 16)
      - Administrative Committee (Box 16)
      - Board of Managers (Box 16)
      - Constitution and By-Laws Committee (Box 16)
      - Finance Committee (Box 16)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Little Josephine (Box 16)
  - 1961-1965
    - General (Box 17)
    - General Board (Box 17)
    - General, 2 folders (Box 17)
    - General, 2 folders (Box 18)
    - General
      - Committee on Policy and Strategy (Box 18)
      - Emergency Commission Religion and Race (Box 18)
    - General Board, 3 folders (Box 19)
    - General
      - Administrative and Finance Committee (Box 19)
      - Business and Finance (Box 20)
      - Business and Finance, Executive Committee (Box 20)
      - Constitution and By-Laws Committee (Box 20)
      - Nominating Committee (Box 20)
      - Personnel Committee (Box 20)
      - Policy and Strategy Committee (Box 20)
    - Joint Committee on Relations (Box 21)
    - Special Committee on Structure and Function, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - Structures Committee, 1963; 2 folders (Box 21)
    - Structures and Functions Committee, 3 folders (Box 22)
    - Broadcasting and Film Commission
      - Business and Finance (Box 22)
      - Board of Managers (Box 22)
      - Executive Committee (Box 22)
      - Joint Committee, Board of Managers (Box 22)
    - Division of Christian Life and Work (Box 23)
    - Division of Home Missions
      - Co-Operative Planning Board (Box 23)
      - Department of Migrant Work (Box 23)
      - Executive Board (Box 23)
      - Migrants (Box 23)
    - Interchurch Center, General (Box 23)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 23)
- General Files
  - A, 1956-1959 (Box 24)
  - American Bible Society, 1956-1965; 2 folders (Box 24)
  - American Bible Society, 3 folders (Box 25)
  - American Mothers Committee (Box 25)
  - American Mothers Committee, Board of Directors, 1957-1959 (Box 25)
  - Article - "When My Husband Nearly Left the Church", 1959 (Box 26)
  - B, 1957-1959 (Box 26)
  - Book of the Month Club, 1957 (Box 26)
  - Brides to Be article by Mrs. Peale (Box 26)
  - Brown, Alice (Box 26)
  - C, 1956-1959 (Box 26)
  - Christmas, 1949-1956 (Box 27)
  - Christmas gifts, 1958 (Box 27)
  - Cook Christian Training School (Box 27)
  - Current Sermons (Box 27)
  - D, 1957-1959 (Box 27)
  - Dickler, 1957 (Box 27)
  - E, 1957-1959 (Box 27)
  - Eby, A. James (Box 27)
  - Elizabeth (Box 27)
  - F, 1957-1959 (Box 27)
  - Farwell (Box 28)
  - Foundation for Christian Living
    - General (Box 28)
    - Board of Directors (Box 28)
    - Book Promotion (Box 28)
    - Book Sales, 1951 (Box 28)
    - Booklet Idea folder (Box 28)
    - Booklets (Box 28)
    - Financial Reports, 2 folders (Box 28)
    - General (Box 28)
    - General Correspondence (Box 28)
    - Investments, 2 folders (Box 28)
    - Look Reports, 2 folders (Box 28)
    - Personnel, 2 folders (Box 29)
    - Plate room (Box 29)
    - Promotion, 3 folders (Box 29)
    - Sermon Publications Committee (Box 29)
    - Radio Reports (Box 29)
    - Youth Booklet (Box 29)
  - Friends Seminary
  - G, 1957-1959 (Box 29)
  - Gill, 1961 (Box 29)
  - Graham, Billy (Box 30)
  - Guideposts Article, "Supreme Court and School Prayer" (Box 30)
  - Guideposts Editorial (Box 30)
  - Guideposts investments, 2 folders (Box 30)
  - H (Box 30)
  - Hall Syndicate (Box 30)
  - Hooven letters (Box 31)
  - I (Box 31)
  - Inspirational Book Service (Box 31)
  - Interchurch Center (Box 31)
  - Interior Decorating (Box 31)
  - Investments (Box 31)
  - J, 1957-1959 (Box 32)
  - Japan International Christian University (Box 32)
  - John, 2 folders (Box 32)
  - K (Box 32)
  - L (Box 32)
  - Layman's Leaders Institute, 1960 (Box 33)
  - Mc (Box 33)
  - M (Box 33)
  - Marble Collegiate Church, 2 folders (Box 33)
  - Margaret, 2 folders (Box 33)
  - Marquis, Sarah, travel agency (Box 33)
  - Marquis Who's Who (Box 34)
  - Masterpiece Treasury, Inc. (Box 34)
  - Memo to the Board (Box 34)
  - Murphy's Furrier (Box 34)
  - Music Appreciation records (Box 34)
  - N (Box 34)
  - National Council of Churches (Box 34)
  - National Foundation for Medical Education, 2 folders (Box 34)
  - N.Y. State Federation of Women's Clubs, 2 folders (Box 34)
  - O (Box 34)
  - Orient shopping (Box 34)
  - Pa - Pi (Box 35)
  - Pawling Property, 2 folders (Box 35)
  - Po - Pz (Box 35)
  - Protestant International Chapel Fund, 1959 (Box 35)
  - P.E.O., 2 folders (Box 36)
  - Photographs (Box 36)
  - Preparatory schools (Box 36)
  - Presbyterian Church of U.S.A., 2 folders (Box 36)
  - Protestant Council of the City of N.Y., 3 folders (Box 36)
  - Protestant Motion Picture ratings, 2 folders (Box 36)
  - Q (Box 36)
  - R (Box 36)
  - Record Sales, 2 folders (Box 37)
  - Reformed Church in America
    - General, 2 folders (Box 37)
    - Audio-visual committee (Box 37)
    - Board of Domestic Missions
      - [General?], 1952-1953 (Box 37)
      - Department of Evangelism (Box 37)
      - Executive Committee (Box 37)
      - Finance Committee (Box 37)
      - Indian Committee (Box 38)
      - Policy Committee (Box 38)
      - Women's Work Department (Box 38)
    - Visual Aid Service (Box 38)
  - Regretted Speaking engagements (Box 38)
  - Religion in American Life, Inc. (Box 38)
  - Reprints of articles (Box 38)
  - Reservation orders (Box 38)
  - S (Box 38)
  - Sermon Cabinet collections (Box 39)
  - Sermons by Dr. Peale (Box 39)
  - Sorosis
    - General, 2 folders (Box 39)
    - Anniversary Carbons (Box 39)
    - Executive Committee (Box 39)
    - Invitations, 2 folders (Box 39)
    - Luncheon (Box 40)
  - Speaking engagements (Box 40)
  - Speeches made (Box 40)
  - Standard Education Society (Box 40)
  - Syracuse University
    - General, 2 folders (Box 40)
    - Board of Trustees, 2 folders (Box 40)
    - Development Plan, 1961-1963 (Box 41)
    - Youth Development Center (Box 41)
  - 1030 5th Ave. Corp. Financial Statements, 1958-1959 (Box 41)
  - 1025 5th Ave (Box 41)
  - 25th Anniversary invitations (Box 41)
  - United Church Women, 1959-1960 (Box 41)
  - Volk, Kurt H., Inc. (Box 41)
  - W (Box 41)
  - What's Your Trouble
    - [General], 2 folders (Box 41)
    - 1952-1953, 3 folders (Box 42)
    - Financial Statements (Box 42)
  - 1957-1959
    - A-C, 3 folders (Box 42)
    - Companion Pocket Cross (Box 42)
    - D (Box 42)
    - Daniels, Charles R. (Box 42)
    - Elizabeth (Box 42)
    - F-G, 2 folders (Box 43)
    - General Correspondence (Box 43)
    - H-J, 3 folders (Box 43)
    - Johnson, Mr. and Mrs. Horace (Box 43)
    - K-L, 3 folders (Box 43)
    - M-P, 4 folders (Box 44)
    - Peale, Mrs., letters and memos (Box 44)
    - Q-W, 8 folders (Box 44)
    - Volk, Inc. (Box 45)
    - Y-Z, 2 folders (Box 45)
    - Correspondence, 1957-1960 (Sep); 4 folders (Box 45)
    - Correspondence, 1960, Oct-Dec; 2 folders (Box 46)